soft engineering radio episode 132 top
10 architecture mistakes with Owen woods
today's show is brought to you by
audible please visit audible podcast.com
slash ser for a free audiobook download
[Music]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at s e - radio dotnet
I see radio brings you relevant and
detailed discussions and interviews on
software engineering topics every 10
days thanks to our audience and the
partners listed on our website possible
[Music]
welcome everybody to software
engineering radio this episode is a
discussion with Owen woods yes that's
how you pronounce the name about
software architecture mistakes and what
you can learn from them but before we
get to the actual content let me briefly
introduce our sponsors this episode is
sponsored by audible.com the internet's
leading provider of spoken audio
entertainment they have over 51,000
titles you can download and listen to on
all your devices like your ipod whatever
among them a lot of Science and
Technology stuff they have novels they
also have a specifically interesting
science fiction section so and as a
podcast listener I guess there's a
chance that you like to consume
information via listening
so I guess audible is a good match for
for you guys for your listeners as an NC
radio listener you can get one book for
free if you subscribe it's at
[Music]
it's a read I don't know by whom it's
read but it's important that you check
who reads stuff because a good reader
can make a big difference and it was
good reader just don't know the name so
if you want to try it out go to audible
podcast.com slash slash ser and give it
a try thanks to audible for supporting
this podcast
ok and now let's get on with the actual
content that is cache with oh and what's
about software architecture mistakes
once again this is an episode we
recalled at the jowl conference in
Aarhus
mark and what is it September October is
2008 and today we're talking about top
10 software architecture and architect
mistakes our guest today is Owen woods
hello thank you very nice to be here
absolutely thanks for being on the show
so before we start obviously why don't
you introduce yourself our audience my
name is Owen woods I'm a work working
software architect I'm not a researcher
or someone who kind of writes books and
is training for a living you know doing
software architecture since the late
1990s I'd guess started my career with
bull working on their version of a
product called tuxedo which some of you
may know spent some time with Sybase
working on database system system
management also working as a consultant
I've worked for start-up interest
technologies in California and most
recently I've worked for UBS investment
bank for nearly three years and most
recently I now work for Barclays Global
Investors in London as a software
architect specifically on one major
program apex which is our new portfolio
management system and of course although
you say you a you are a working Software
Architect you don't just write books you
did also write a book I did in fact
co-author a book with my colleague Nick
rozanski who has also in fact just
joined Barclays Global Investors so you
never know maybe there's another one
lurking out there somewhere and will put
their book URL into the show notes of
course and there's this good free stuff
on the site to download so thanks cool
so before we actually look at those top
10 things obviously you call yourself an
architect so you probably well you must
have some understanding what it means to
be an architect so why don't you briefly
express or explain the actual work you
do because this is always an interesting
question I mean what do architects do
indeed it's a very good question and I
separate architects into three buckets
actually there are people who do
enterprise architecture and I definitely
don't do that
and they I'd summarize them they're the
people who work out what systems need to
be built and how they should be linked
together there's the infrastructure
architect and I definitely don't do that
either those are the people who are
experts in how the company should use a
particular technology stack or kind of
technology so you might have you know
data architects who
decide how you database we should be
used and so on middleware architects and
what about messaging and app service and
then this is the sort of accident I am
which and we're the people who build
systems or rather we lead teams to build
a systems yeah we're a bit like team
leaders except that we don't end up in
reporting to us so we tend to have the
ultimate responsibility for all the
technical decisions made in the system
development lifecycle now but of course
inevitably because you're a sponsor for
a lot of decisions you're really
responsible for other people's right so
it's a question of making the biggest
decision of yourself and then
shepherding other people to make
decisions you think a sound yeah that
kind of framework so how would you
define architecture oh that's a very
good question actually my flippant
response to that is it's the set of
design decisions that if you get them
wrong they'll cancel your project
they're the ones you really have to get
right right another another slightly
flippant but maybe more useful
definition is they tend to be the design
decisions that people outside the
project care about and indirectly
perhaps but they can see them on their
effectively write the definition I like
to use is all the stuff you want to be
consistent all throughout the system for
reasons of achieving non-functional
requirements or reliability or
maintainable and that's another great
definition then definitely the scope of
the decision you know those things that
separates a design decision one designer
working in a lab system and an
architectural decision yeah which is
something that effects the whole system
now I think something or one definition
is often used talks about granularity
and scale and I think that's probably
not useful because you might even have
on a very fine-grained level certain
architectural constraints like for
example the locking protocol to be used
it's very detailed about how you access
a resource but it's still architectural
because it's cross-cutting and kind of
global I completely so okay then so I
guess your your top 10 architecture
mistakes are I would guess basically a
kind of lessons to learn from working as
an architect and and seeing how people
go wrong right that's right um 10 of
courses are some arbitrary nice real
numbers and I'm sure if I'd carried on
thinking perhaps I gotta come up with a
few more background is I'm a member of
the International Association of
software architects I sir I so home to
or give you're after it so they have a
program where they
find publications who are interested in
in in articles being written and
approached me and asked me for an idea
and I came up with this idea and then I
think somebody Jo saw the idea and so
invited me to give the talk based on it
so tens perhaps a nice round number but
the way I came up with these specific
problems is they're all ones I've seen
their own mistakes I've seen made more
than once yeah okay and they've tended
to be painful right okay so um let's
start with the first one
it's called scoping woes yes this is
where there's obviously two problems
with scope one is you get it to narrow
and when you get to your broad and
you'll tend to get different people and
the project stakeholders if you will
pulling in different directions on this
is that it's very common to see in our
senior management will decide that a
very very minimal system is exactly what
they're after because they'd rather not
pay for anything bigger because the
budget is rather fixed and then you'll
get perhaps an end user or perhaps
somebody else that maybe even a systems
administrator deciding that there's a
whole lot of features that they'd like
added yeah it's really aren't required
but they can make a good case for them
and scope and either direction is a
problem and actually functional scopes
one thing I know how to do this or I
should it shouldn't do this but actually
the thing that often comes back to kill
you is the non-functional scopes so it's
it's it's getting the scope of things
like how much security you really need
yeah and you can end up in in a morass
of security protocols and people and
technology that you didn't really need
or you can't go live because you missed
out an important that's it's it's
probably some of those non-functional
requirements for which it's not
necessarily easy to explain the
trade-offs I mean like every of course
everybody wants security and scalability
everything but all of those come with a
cost that's absolutely true but that
cost is sometimes hard to put into
numbers I guess that's what some of the
of the problems come from indeed I mean
my classic example is that if you get
the security scope to narrow the the
hidden cost is you can't you're live
with the system right because somebody
at the last minute will tell you yeah to
narrow they won't come and find you and
tell you it's too narrow you've got to
go out and find them and check that it's
wide enough yeah that's a very big cost
if yeah if the system is business critic
have you seen that that a system that is
perceived
to be really important for the for the
company or organization going going
going further that that it has been
cancelled for reasons of security really
right before it went live never
cancelled but in the security software
industry there are many stories of big
product releases being pulled at the
last minute because somebody hasn't
checked off a verification test yeah or
somebody didn't realize that some extra
protocol was required is it's not that
you can the project don't get me wrong
it's not that serious yeah but suddenly
you've missed a release window right
actually that might be the hidden cost
it's the fact that three months later
the system is less all the product
release is is less valuable yeah so of
course I mean you know just highlighting
problems and mistakes is one thing and
it's useful in itself but maybe we have
some remedies what can we do I mean how
do we how do we how do we what do we do
to hopefully get scoping better right I
need you to asking hard questions yes
yes I mean scope is just tough to get
right but the key thing really is is
making sure that you understand who the
decision-makers and the important people
are who have a say in scope and who will
be affected by scope and get them on
board early
it's very rich to the second point is
about talking to stakeholders but the
two are very closely related but really
the first one is what happens typically
with when you don't cast your
stakeholders right widely and I guess
the other thing that's related is then
if you have the stakeholders that you
make it clear to them what it means to
either not have a certain thing in scope
or putting something in scope and then
talking about the cost of adding that
like they can make a real good decision
that's a very good point
yeah just informing the stakeholders
often really doesn't achieve anything
because they'll simply not they really
won't understand the trade-off that
you're trying to get them to make and
you often you have to bring you know
senior managers the classic thing is you
have to bring the trade-off on three
three PowerPoint slides right give them
the options get them to make a decision
right but even I found you know
sometimes you do with an enterprise
security group and really they've they
won't really pick out the decision
you're trying to get them to make
they'll really just give you further
advice right it's not really what you're
after
yeah yeah because they want Don
to be responsible maybe that's probably
part of it yeah okay so the as you said
the next one not talking to as many
stakeholders as you should it's very
related so can you can you explain that
and also distinguish that from the first
one
sure well as I think it might be no I
think of it it might be cause and effect
really yeah only one of the effects of
not talking to enough stakeholders I'm
taking them seriously and really
listening to them is that you'll end up
with skill problems you may end up with
other problems as well of course yes I
mean for most systems the classic
stakeholder is the end user and probably
the acquirer so the person paying the
bills I'm talking about in-house system
yeah the problem is is that for many
teams that's where it starts and stops
and they don't really think any further
than that but if you think about the
lifecycle of a big system going into the
enterprise environment there's a lot of
other people who care I mean classic
people would include people who have to
support the system it may be different
to the development team or might be the
same but you've said they've got two
hats the infrastructure folks operating
areas or people who'll operate it
absolutely people I can't depress
compliance audit control all those
people especially if you're in a
regulated industry such as medical or
finance they have a lot of say and so
there's a whole lot of people who who
aren't if you like business users I mean
they in a sense they don't necessarily
contribute anything directly to our use
of the system but get it wrong for them
and there's probably a lot of pain just
down the road for you yeah you'll have
to force the changes in another
characteristic of some of those groups
is probably also that they're not going
to actively you know come to you and
tell you you know here is what we need
they just sit there passively and then
if you don't conform to their
expectations your hosts that's
absolutely the case the classic problem
were dealing with an infrastructure
group and to be fair to them you know
they're very busy people and the result
and everything but the problem is they
do sit there passively and then at the
last minute your system turns up and
then they'll complain about not being
involved now of course you didn't
realize they had to be yeah and it's
that's just where experience really the
organizational knowledge comes in yeah
these people need to be involved earlier
the other thing is to describe your
architecture your system in a way that
they understand that's where this idea
of architectural views yeah don't draw
one
picture because no one will understand
it yes drill pictures aimed at the
different people who care yeah right so
yeah I mean obviously the some of
sometimes I get the impression with
those groups that they well obviously
obviously they don't directly benefit
from the introduction of a new system
it's more a chore for them to have to
operate it and that's how it seems
perfectly true yes organization as a
whole benefits so they do not but but
that's maybe why they're kind of
passively sitting there and not actively
you know I need this I need this
requirement it solves my problem because
you don't solve they're perfectly true
yeah I mean I I separate stakeholders a
deposit of a negative right yes I want
the system to be there and to succeed
very points to compliance every new
system is a risk why would they want it
in production and so they it's their job
to block it it can be argued and of
course there many compliance people are
very positive to be fair in their thing
but if you look at it from a pure
self-interest point of view you know why
would they want your system in
production exactly yeah yeah and that's
really the problem is that get those
people on the side as early as you can't
because they need to be your friend
another another thing in this context is
that that I've experienced with
especially with large customers is that
they already have a bunch of existing
frameworks platforms tools libraries for
a logging for example yeah and if you
don't use that your system won't fit
into their operations infrastructure and
then again you're screwed so so knowing
their technical requirements is
something that's very very related here
- absolutely and you know it's often
painful for the development team they
don't excuse this library or I mean I
worked for UBS investment bank for
nearly three years and they they have
various system monitoring things that
you have to do there they are good
reason and that's why they have reliable
systems every development team
about them but you know are there for a
reason
if you don't standardize it can't be
supported out so with it one customer I
worked for I had the same kind of thing
but they weren't they didn't document
their frameworks and they had no people
that actually could come to your project
and help you get things right so you had
to use it but you basically couldn't I
sure that was very but I've tended to
find that's the norm really yeah you
must do all this good luck yeah what's
going to happen and if you get it wrong
will tell you just about
just before you're going to predict
right yes that's that's and then it
becomes a power play of whether you get
it running or not depending on who is
more important in the company
whether the business unit can swing
their their influence yeah okay next one
focusing on functions or the other way
of course is forgetting the
non-functional stuff right indeed yes I
mean this is this is the classic problem
where you ask them believe what you want
the system to do and they'll give you a
laundry list of functions as we've
already mentioned some of they really
need and some of they just kind of like
if you can do them what they'll never
tell you is all the implicit quality
requirements and it's got to be
available during these hours a failure
cost them this much money a minute
there's this many users will be using it
and the it must be able to process this
many items and an overnight batch within
a one-hour window while the database is
still in use by another region there's
all these things about how the system's
going to do it now and I yet have to
meet it's any kind of end user to be
honest who really can help me specify
those very precisely you really have to
go out assert some things are correct
find out if they're not find potential
clashes with the way the organization
works and other systems learn from other
systems especially like me you're quite
new to an organization find out where
others have had those problems and then
really go through a checklist of all the
different qualities that you think might
be relevant as to yeah what are the top
three how do they and there was the
trickiest bit how do they trade off
against each right yeah yeah exactly
there's a problem with the
non-functional it's they always kind of
balance between various of them another
thing that I read recently I don't
remember where oh it was in Tom DeMarcos
new book the the adrenaline junkies
where he talks about straw man where he
says and that goes back to our scoping
thing also where you have to really
build a straw man scenario that says you
know we're going to build a system but
it requires a reboot every night and we
need one week per year to install the
new version and it's gonna be over
Christmas is this okay for you and of
course it's a ridiculous statement I
think it provokes the stakeholders to
become you know basically too
protesting no no no no it needs to be
this way date I have done similar things
you've got to be careful how often you
do it but I have done it to provoke a
reaction and also you find out if
they've read the document don't come
back with any complaints you know they
didn't read it what they say yeah that's
a great idea let's find that book it's
actually it's a nice book it's like a
collection of 95 patterns or something
okay that they detected in projects
about behaviors that work and don't work
okay and yeah we'll have an episode on
su radio at some point we'll put those
guys very good
so it with is no non-functional
qualities the problem is often that you
have to somehow make them concrete into
numbers like we need a reliability of
such and such many nines or whatever
what's your experience can you make
typical stakeholders actually commit to
numbers or are they're afraid of being
concrete so they can always say they
wanted more than you did I haven't
really found them being afraid of being
concrete of more in anything it's the
opposite if anything when if you make it
concrete they'll just simply sign it off
because it looks very precise and
scientific so everything is going to be
fine and it's related they really think
about what not having available on a
Saturday morning means and they don't
necessarily think through the scenarios
I what you sometimes have to do is a
little bit like at a much more formal
level sort of high process approach at
the sei is a time method for assessing
software architects is all very scenario
pay there you can do a similar thing
much much less formally with a few
sentences to kind of illustrate to
somebody what a particular quality
requirement he is going to imply for
them right they can I don't know
processor thousand units per hour in the
in the nightly batch this means we can't
process more than two regions overnight
and then they go oh no no hang on right
and you say well you've only got two
regions they go no no no but we're about
to have six right we've covered a
quality requirement and some who are
still difficult because things like
security you can you can do scenarios
but unless the person is a security
specialist and use of things like threat
modeling and thinking about security
it's quite tricky the ready to get
people to
to react one way or the other and most
of us frankly are not experts in
security ourselves yes so it there are
still qualities that it's tricky on
evolutions another great one I mean the
essay I've got this great example of one
of their training manuals about stimulus
to the system is changed database from
my sequel to Oracle requirement is must
be able to do it in 20 Monday's well I
don't know about you I don't know how
long it would take to change the
database system then I'm not quite sure
how I'd work it out without trying it
which would be a lot of work so some of
them are just hard yeah to be honest I
think in some areas like evolution
they're really more aspirations than
requirements you necessarily can
honestly say you can meet because
they're very hard to test yeah right
yeah but but it gives you at least
topics to focus on like your database
thing example you know that database
independence is important so you think
about and you you know you take
precautions about making things from the
database not show up in the API since
that's perfect so it puts the fear of
God in here in the right areas as I said
it can be useful yes so the next one
bubbles don't crash right line
description what's the problem with that
well it's the it's not so much that
pictures are a bad thing but I'm a very
pictorial thinker I find a lot of
software designers are as our designers
and traditional industries to
traditional engineering industries - the
problem is they either a3 Visio diagram
full of boxes and small arrows all with
slightly different dashes on the arrow
stems and different shading in the boxes
that everyone's forgotten what it means
yeah or equally well the five box
PowerPoint slide with a different type
of border on every box and lots of
errors joining them but you're not quite
sure what the errors and sometimes those
things have their place when Nick
renowned scan I wrote a book we we refer
to those as cartoons a sort of informal
informal architectural sketches I was
actually not how for example the se I
use the term air they use it differently
but I mean how kind of idea was sort of
having done all the formal stuff if you
need to explain it to somebody quickly
you'd sit down with a piece of paper and
a pencil you draw five boxes that was
our idea you'd be sketching a card don't
that's useful but if you don't have the
the actual description somewhere you
actually don't know what their
components of the system are or how they
fit together and the snag is is that if
if you do do it all with some strange
rotation you don't bother defining every
one of the things they understand it and
actually no one does yeah so this this I
mean you kind of hit a nerve with with
me because as you maybe know I'm
modeling and and so first of all I tend
to prefer textual languages of a
graphical ones but that is not
discussion so I distinguish between
modeling and diagramming and the diagram
is kind of your cartoons right it's it's
a visualization of something that
doesn't need to be formally defined but
the notation must be clear not not
formally clear but intuitively clear and
then on the other side you have models
which you can actually process generate
code from and validate that's something
completely different
yeah to be fair absolutely I in this
presentation particular I neatly gloss
over this right which in fact if any of
my engineers listening to this they'll
be shaping up the shading up their iPods
because I'm always telling people off
for drawing pictures and opening a model
behind it yes so for me the picture is
simply representation of the model yeah
which is why you know we try and use
some tools like you know magic draw is
one particular one we use that has a
real uml model behind right it's not
just a picture in Visio yeah to me
actually doing the pictures is often not
that valuable because you can't use the
information for anything if the stuffs
in a in a model and you can never get
through the repository yeah you can ask
it questions you may have to write
scraps of code to ask the questions but
you can ask questions and you can get
answers back and it's tremendously more
valuable so so in this context you say
that using box and line descriptions is
is a is a mistake is a problem it's
intentional it's a potential problem if
it is used in this non formal way so
turning it around do you think there is
a benefit to describing architectures
formally well I think that very much
depends on the scale and the environment
with every one every deliverable but
especially architecture deliverables the
question to ask is who's going to use it
providing you have a constituency some
people who care that there is some
formality behind your architecture and
that they can
animate it or generate something off it
or just simply maybe run reports on it
right then it's useful to have some
level of formality especially machine
process right machine processable
formality that's what I mean before
mallet is my definition of formality I
don't write any tool that you know
checks constraint on it or generates
code or right because I came originally
from a formal method see it's a
tremendous a tremendous amount of
writing upside down A's on whiteboard so
they'd not be able to process them the
formal methods communities moved a long
way beyond that actually I tend to use
the term processable as opposed to
formal talking for exactly that reason I
always something I always think to
myself when I'm typing stuff into a UML
tool supposing I am doing that yeah how
could I pull this out later yeah would
it be useful so you just said suppose I
do that do you actually use you
regularly and do you use it for
diagramming for communicating ideas or
do you really use it in a formal way
formal being defined in the sense we
just said I do use UML I'd say I must
say as a percentage of my time it's
probably actually producing models and
diagrams it's quite a small amount of it
but yes I mean every architecture
document I produce I do use UML right to
describe my main structural views then I
always describe UML is it really sucks
as an architectural description language
but I haven't yet found a better one
well yeah well especially one in in
general use that I can buy a tool for so
that's the point because I well and this
goes actually this is more like my
opinion and I maybe should keep it out
of this episode but I think just briefly
I think a big a big sweet spot is
actually defining your own language for
your that captures your architectural
abstractions of your system or product
line or whatever because then you don't
have to shoehorn on your abstractions
into an existing generic language but
rather you express things as a language
as they are defined in your environment
so that exactly I mean I think
yeah actually I think we're in sort of
violent agreement okay
I mean in fact the one good thing about
UML really is is that you don't need to
put up with the language as it shipped
it's it's extensible in some sense and
tools have just caught up with the
extensibility of adding proper
stereotypes and adding yeah I'm fine
so of course you stuck with the
metamodel yeah I just have to have to
deal with that yes I'm actually very
interested in whether some form of
practical in fact it would be textual
DSL can be produced and we can all work
together to do a kind of spring-like
things something sits on top of spring
components something like that who are
you your architecture is actually part
of the system it's not a separate
artifact actually this is exactly my
point there it's a kind of executable
architecture so from from from just
having verbal or pictorial input as an
architect you go to concrete processable
usable artifacts that are part of the
system indeed and today of course we do
that by doing the first cut coding we
create a java packages we put the main
classes in place we put a lot of other
empty classes in case and we say to
everyone work in the framework and
that's kind of our executable
architecture but of course we lose
two-thirds of the architectural
information yes president code
absolutely so that's where you need well
I think we we need to talk because it's
this approach currently in in progress
with a couple of customers oh and it
works really nice but this is another
thing okay next one is forgetting that
it needs to be built right well this is
the classic problem if you're if you're
using spending too much time on UML tool
and not enough time in an IDE it's
deciding that we're going to use this
latest sexiest bit of technology which
is just going to be fantastic and of all
these benefits now forgetting the fact
that the team who are going to build it
with you are profoundly unenthusiastic
about about what you've you've you've
decided to pick up I don't really want
to learn it and actually your
infrastructure guys don't think they can
run it I mean these are all things which
have happened to real systems I have
shame face to be been involved in is
that and it needn't even be a new bit of
technology it's just a new way of using
it perhaps there's that you can only
move as fast as your underlying platform
and and your sort of development
constraints right if you know the team
it can build it if you don't have the
money if you don't have the time if you
don't have the infrastructure
environment if you don't have the
support guys there's just no point in
deciding you're gonna do this new sexy
thing by all means come play without a
Sunday afternoon but on Monday morning
back at work you've got to have that
reality check
yeah so this is also a little bit the
the ivory tower architect problem right
so you have an architect who only you
know has on cloud seven with concepts as
opposed to actually looking at the code
and dealing with the real world that we
need I mean my pet bugbear at the moment
is so uh and the number of Central
architecture teams who don't have a
delivery responsibility for systems who
have decided that you should build
systems using so uh and uh yet really
have to find all that many what I would
call stream architects the guys actually
building systems we have terribly
enthusiastic about so uh seems to bring
along a package with it yeah and it's a
classic problem if if you're sitting
centrally and you're looking at
principles and concepts it's very easy
not to follow through mentally in the
how would I actually build with it and
run it in there adduction yeah yeah this
is another thing where I think concepts
are important in architecture so you you
you I mean you think about things like
decoupling and I don't know
decentralization compensation as opposed
to locking it's important but but as you
say you have to you have to find a way
to bring it down to the real to the real
guys who absolutely we have to work with
it and make it relevant for them stayed
and make sure also that mean that the
from my I've observed in myself as much
as others I'm pointing the finger at
myself here is you download the new cool
language the classic at the moment being
the functional language is you download
it up you play with it on your MacBook
which of course you can't connect to a
corporate network because you you use
pcs it's completely isolated and you
play through a whole lot of tutorials
and you go in suddenly very excited
about the potential functional languages
you haven't actually worked through a
real problem that you might hit and in
the real deployment environment until
you've done a bit more of that you need
to keep your enthusiasms under control
it is my view really yeah ok next one
lack of platform precision well this was
a problem I had very specifically when
working for a company I sure they won't
mom using their name into trust
technologies who still exists they're
there now a subsidiary of Sony and
Philips they're based in California and
they do digital rights management system
is still in business well that their
subsidiaries a very very large company
ok they're mainly famous not for their
technology but for suing Microsoft and
winning most companies haven't but
they were a lot of patents in the area a
specific problem we had there actually
was versions of the Oracle 8c client and
the fact that I count from the exact
numbers was something like eight point
zero point seven three is fundamentally
incompatible eight point seven point
fifteen and none of us quite realizing
you're thinking well it's eight point
zero it's all Oracle right if you just
work and actually it just it causes all
kinds of problems on the server and
caused internal server disasters I have
observed there's actually quite a lot of
places and I started my career as I
mentioned as a system software engineer
so working on a product called cedar and
you know we always used to cuss at
customers who used to report bugs that
were quite obviously mismatched
configurations of course well I didn't I
didn't put the pieces together in my
mind and actually have quite hard in the
real world to put all the pieces
together now and unfortunately I mean
Java and.net I mean to be fair I think
of massively simplified this but even in
those environments you can't just assume
it's gonna work on the next jgm and
someone else's JVM without any problems
if you buy a Azul appliance you're gonna
need to go and check that all of your
funky locking code actually works the
way you think it does because you may be
relying on a side effect that you're
totally unaware of there this is this
hole in concurrency that kind of thing
becomes especially a problem doing it
and I've come across a lot together also
in database systems yeah especially
interrupts between things like you've
got a cyber base database in an Oracle
database and you're replicating between
them right it's all just meant to work
and then you need to upgrade one small
part of one of the products and suddenly
all the dates appear with the wrong
century or something right and it's
because some Engineer some was reset of
default that was maybe you should always
have been applying yeah actually fixed a
bug it's not going to help you yeah
another thing that that comes to mind in
that context and maybe is related is the
the trying to be platform independent to
an to a degree that is kind of pointless
so because I mean adding five different
interaction layers of course as
complexity and all that so trying to be
too independent of whatever platform
persistence middleware probably is also
an anti-pattern that you might want to
be on the lookout for I think maybe a
fair point actually yes is that you you
can build this tottering stack of
abstractions I mean I have seen the
system where you know people start with
a pub/sub
they sort of build a queueing
abstraction on top and then realize they
need multiple point delivery I kind of
rebuild to pop something on top of the
queue you know it's just absolutely
it's like Dan Heywood the independent
consultant who was widely known for a
bit for criticizing OMGs MDA
I mean it can always says you got to
lock yourself into something I'd rather
lock myself into Java than UML alright
and you know at some point you have to
get concrete it is a fine line though
because I mean of course you don't want
to see I don't know angled brackets from
XML and and specific database specific
code in your applications but on the
other hand trying to so that you want to
abstract from that but trying to
abstract from let's say a communications
paradigm indeed it's it's probably mean
the things to look out for really I
think the the fundamental parts of your
platform right over you define that in
your environment so for example an
embedded guy I guess it's chipset it's
hard to either completely ignore the
fact you're in our particular chips in
my environment it's much more about the
fact that we use for example WebLogic
server Ryan you know sure it's a
standard thing and in theory we can move
into JBoss tomorrow but actually you
know we know that we've heavy reliance
on j2ee and in fact there are situations
where we make a decision that we're
gonna be quite reliant on the particular
server that we're using so what I try to
tell my customers is that they should
stay away from making their their their
application code dependent on a specific
technology but of course they should be
relying on a paradigm black for example
it's perfectly OK to assume pops up or
messaging but it's not useful to
necessarily code typical api's directly
in your application so there should be
an abstraction of the technology but not
of the paradigm yes that's a pretty good
rule I think to me with the problem of
course being the lowest lowest cannot
come under abstraction problem right
except oh for example I mean typical RV
if you're really gonna use it in a
high-performance system it's quite hard
to ignore all of tip codes api's
right and then and then there comes the
next the next thing which I then you
know if this reply comes then what I
typically add is that if you do
technology specific things make sure you
I salute it and you're aware so
if you need to change something you know
where you need to touch things so you
don't have the technology you know
spread through like a cancer through all
your system but you have it isolated to
certain whatever methods framework path
or whatever absolutely I think yeah the
key messages understand your
dependencies yeah where you'd have a
good night yes that's and that's the
meta point but absolutely it's if you're
gonna lock yourself into TIBCO RV know
where your contact point right are and
know what you rely on and yes that
that's the best advice you can ever
think about performance assumptions yes
so this this point performance is really
just a poster child here for making
assumptions particularly about
non-functional requirements assuming
that because your application server
offers a clustering feature that it's
the clustering feature you require and
then it works the way that you need it
to work here assuming that because
database vendor my my classic example
would be assuming a database vendor has
benchmarked something at a speed that
you could get anywhere near it
I mean the database vendor I know most
customers never did yeah reasons
considering how much effort goes into a
benchmark yeah I think the list goes on
and on really it's in a you you cannot
possibly test everything but some things
are going to make a big difference to
you if they turn out to be vastly
different to what you're expecting and
so you need to you know you need to be
testing if you possibly can building
prototypes if and if that's too
expensive or difficult in if any things
like performance models or security
models really try and work through in
your head yeah is this credible that we
could run this this fast or that this
couldn't be broken all their this
honestly could move all the workload in
flight between these machines you know
in many cases you'll come up with a
certain light bulb will go on you'll
realize that's not gonna happen
therefore the following reasons so in
some sense it's also you could rephrase
that as don't believe marketing speak
that possibly is the less vendor this
very friendly version of it yesterday
yeah yeah don't assume that all the
stuff in your environment works the way
that people tell you right yeah and and
then of course what you do against that
is that you do load tests with mock-ups
early right and ability or
we build you know spikes that verify
certain behaviors of your platform right
yeah I mean the best thing is hands-on
testing and this is where I think if
architects aren't on the critical path
coding the application they can a stave
you know hands-on and relevant enough
today to be a full perform a very
valuable function for the project by
building the performance prototype
integrating the security platform and
checking that the security team are
happy with it you know actually checking
the failover works the way I think it
does so that's actually probably a
recommendation on itself which would be
built a prototype that only verifies the
non-functional and and fill the business
logic with sleep statements right pretty
well exactly
yeah that probably helps yeah the next
of your top ten software architects
mistakes is do-it-yourself security
that's right it's it's really doing
yourself infrastructure but security is
the best example that seems to keep
cropping up it's the fact that pretty
well every software engineer if you ask
them in a in a quiet moment will will
will feel that they can probably whip
together good infrastructure such as a
cryptography algorithm yeah and it's not
only work with real experts and you
realize that there's a bit more to it
that it dawns on you that actually you
probably count there is a reason that
security products for example tend to
cost money and tend to be quite
complicated because the problems they're
solving are complicated yeah and there's
a real danger if you do blunder forwards
with with a little bit of knowledge just
enough to be dangerous yeah then you're
likely to cause problems later ones that
may only come out in production
because it's it's when the system is
actually in use you find that perhaps it
doesn't scale the way you thought it did
or you've tried to write your own
cluster and it really doesn't have the
failure characteristics you need and in
security I think it's especially true
that because writing the algorithm of
course is only half the story you have
to use the algorithm in a system that is
secure as a system otherwise you
introduce all kinds of backdoors and
stuff absolutely so the algorithm is a
lot of moving parts so they need to be
integrated otherwise you have security
holes right through the process another
thing I think related here is in
addition to not doing it yourself is
also there are some concerns security
certainly is one that you cannot easily
retrofit afterwards that you
to think of and plan for right from the
beginning absolutely right and of course
it's the flip side you don't really want
to lock yourself into a particular
security product so you know at the
right abstractions in your system and
yes I mean all of these qualities are
hard to retrofit afterwards so making
good choices about what abstractions you
need in your system and then using
proven reusable infrastructure it makes
a lot of sense in most cases right
there's there always the googles and
they're a little bit different yeah for
them it makes sense to build their own
because they need a different set but
for most of us using the stuff off the
shelf is a good first step yeah okay the
next one is it actually reminds me of
the interview here it's called no
disaster recovery plan might smear off
the interview is actually that we're
this is the second part giving the first
part of the interview the recorder died
and so anyway note it's not a recovery
plan it did you can never well that's
the lesson you can never predict what's
gonna fail right and something's always
gonna fail that's right and most of the
systems that we work on businesses or
organizations are pretty dependent on
them it's quite rare today to find a
system of any size that you can remove
it from the organization and the
organization continues at anything like
the efficiency profitability and in
certain cases the organization's simply
have to stop that business until the
system is repaired yeah the problem of
course with a disaster recovery it's a
bit like paying for your house insurance
perhaps nobody really wants to do it and
especially up front early in the project
when you've got everything to think
about it's very tempting to push
disaster recovery off because it's not
actually needed until you're in
production the big difficulty with that
is that my experience is that actually
if you introduce disaster recovery
incrementally as you build the system as
you design it it's not a great overhead
for every piece you add you have to work
out how you're going to do recovery or
failover on that piece nothing in
afterwards to a system that's had no
thought of disaster every from the
beginning that goes back to what you
were saying these things are hard to
retrofit right and it's very easy to end
up with a system that actually can't be
efficiently fell to a disaster recovery
site I know end up with all of these
manual steps that have to be done which
are just asking for trouble in a real
disaster yep so this is probably a good
point to remember you guys listeners
that we've had the episode on
fault tolerance patterns with Bob hammer
I guess you know them yes and I guess
this episode ties in here nicely yes
good way look at the B game yeah and
also look at it there's a very good book
whoo I'd have to send you the details
but on high-availability
patterns and systems yeah that's a game
great resource there's also there's a
good book on clusters which it a lot of
this stuff is really aimed at people
building the HOA infrastructure but to
have a deeper understanding of the
patterns yeah really helps you when you
come to make your own stuff highly
available because you know what to avoid
right yeah yeah this would be useful to
get this link and we'll put it into show
notes sure yeah okay
and the last of the ten is to have no
plan to back out no back out plan what
do you mean by that I'm not well that's
when you've decided that you're going to
do the migration you've planned it
carefully you start to do the migration
I mean from from the old system to the
new system indeed and at some point in
that process you realize with horror
you're not going to get this done by say
Monday morning when they're expecting to
use the system or something simply
breaks in my experience actually to be
fair it's often not the application it's
that something has changed in the
infrastructure environment that nobody
was aware will affect this system yeah
and suddenly for example you know the
the clustering isn't working or they
can't hook up to the security system
there's a horrible delay as they try and
get clients connected and they just have
to go back to the previous state the
problem is of course if you haven't got
that previous state
ready to roll back in quickly yeah it's
very difficult and I mean the worst case
is you have to allow for a window of 50%
of your upgrade time potential roll back
which is very own efficient that there's
lots of shortcuts you know you dump your
databases first you make sure that you
if possible you you have two sets of
hardware which is kind of expensive but
maybe you can share them with another
project you deploy into one and then you
came across there's lots of relatively
simple techniques actually but in many
many cases people actually don't think
out there how to roll back as opposed to
just move forwards during a migration
yeah and they can simply leave their
business without a system and there's
very few businesses I'm going to be
happy with that on their Monday morning
yeah was one of my first experiences as
a programmer in the hospital I spent the
weekend going back from Microsoft SQL
Server 6.56 although the stupid
migration tool told me that migrating
from six point zero to six pence was no
problem everything's fine so press the
button and part of failed the data
that's the problem Wizards I know the
smart as they think they're okay so I
guess that brings us to the end of your
top ten is there any 11 that kind of
comes to your mind yet you that you wish
to have added to the top 10 that you now
think of you know no yet but if
listeners have some suggestions they
should send them to me because I'm sure
there's another 10 to be written okay so
okay so anything else you want to leave
our listeners with any words of wisdom
I think they've probably had enough
words from me it's worth though saying
that Software Engineering radio it's a
great resource thank you very much for
doing it and I guess listeners if you've
not paid your subscription a very good
point actually I spent some of the money
of the donations we got today to buy a
new compact flash drive because the
original one failed as I said in the
first recording of this interview but
now some are the second one has a
problem and I have to go back this and
there we have a dr plan and it's money
wisely invested absolutely thanks for
being on the show thank you very much
[Music]
thanks for downloading and listening to
software engineering radio software
engineering radio is an educational
program brought to you by hillside
Europe if you want more information
about the podcast and all the other
episodes visit our website and s/ii -
radio dot length if you want to support
us you can donate to the SU radio team
via the website or you can advertise for
su radio for example by clicking on the
dick reddit delicious and Slashdot
buttons to contact the team please send
email to team at se - radio net or if it
is specific to an episode please use the
comments facility on the website so
other people can react to your comments
this episode of se radio as well as all
other episodes are licensed under a
creative commons 2.5 license please see
the website for details thanks to
Charlie Crowell and the pod safe music
network for the music used in the show
the song is called Vegas hard rock
shuffle
[Music]